Inventory of the James Barron Hope Papers (II) 1820-1923
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Personal Correspondence, 1842-1920. (Box-folder 1:1-7)
  - James [Barron Hope], Richmond, [Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina], 4 June [18]62., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Still working in court; he is in good health; hope for postwar happiness; assurance that the Federal gunboats will never get to Richmond; supposed dispiritedness of the Union troops; report of [Union] General [Silas] Casey being killed [false]; feels that the major battle of Richmond is imminent; please write letters with more details of the children; his love for her.
  - James [Barron Hope],[Richmond, Virginia?], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], 9 July [18]62., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Distress that she is still sick; scolds her for not attending the doctor's appointment he had arranged; he is coming home within the next two weeks; can only stay for a short time; asks for the names of items which she and the children want; assurance that "McClellan and the North have rec[eive]d a blow from which they will not soon recover;" [Union General Ambrose E.] Burnside's army was with [Union General George B.] McC[lellan] during the Seven Days campaign [but Burnside was in North Carolina until 6 July 1862]; he [James Barron Hope] has been offered a staff appointment; love for the family.
  - James [Barron Hope], Richmond, [Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina], 1 February 1863., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Attended church today; sermon was excellent; his young friend Gordon [?] fell asleep during the sermon; grieved at her depression; assures her that if he ever becomes gravely ill, he will send a messenger; spent a night with his cousin I[mogene]; wants her to write more, and longer letters; he is well, and politically optimistic; kisses for the girls and her.
  - A. F. Leonard, Jetersville, Virginia, to J[ames] Barron Hope,[Richmond, Virginia?], 23 June [18]63., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Writing for the second time to request information on where to find a reasonably-priced home; lists several names mentioned to him as possible accommodators; asks for the benefit of his experience in this matter, including probable expenses; usually attends the P[rotestant] E[piscopal] church; would be obliged to him for a letter to any of his acquaintances.
  - [James Barron Hope], [Richmond, Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina?], 28 August [18]63., 4 pages. AL. (Box-folder 1:5)
    The Yankees' latest cavalry probe is no threat; Confederate forces are roughly equal in number to the Federals; Gen[era]l R[obert] E. Lee, plus Major Gen[era]ls [John B.] Hood and [Arnold] Elz[e]y are in Richmond; the town "looks very cheerful;" spent an evening with Uncle S[amuel Barron]; relief at receiving her letter describing Jennie's improved health; look into your housing arrangements, but do not worry; is considering becoming a 'man-milliner' after the war; affection for the family.
    Includes drawing with narration on back from [James Barron Hope], [Richmond, Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina]. Skit of a conversation between a general, a widow, and a "young hopeful." 2 pages.
  - James [Barron Hope],[Richmond, Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina?], 1 September [18]63., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Delighted by her note and the flower sent by Jennie; will visit this month will be around the 20th; have shoes made for the children; loved Nannie's note, with good descriptions and a drawing of Annie; in good spirits, especially since Gen[era]l Lee was just there, looking healthy and cheerful; keep him informed on prospects of success in getting board or lodgings; encouraged that her last note less morbidly self-conscious; thanks God for Jennie's improvement; he will try and get the baby heads [?] although he fears it will be impossible; he is well, and loves her.
    Includes NswCl from [James Barron Hope], [Richmond, Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?]. Article on the advantages of wearing boots and how to have them made. 1 page.
  - James [Barron Hope],[?, Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?], [post 1 September 1863 - ante 11 April 1865]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Has gotten the servants off; things are quiet; had no duties assigned to him, so he visited her father's house and offered his services; they were just now declined; he shall come to her as soon as possible; keep quiet and trust in God.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], n.p., [post 25 July 1864 - ante 11 April 1865]., 2 pages. Incomplete. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Liza [?] has some disease of the spine; Willie Peeks died at Winchester; saw several family friends; fears of a [Federal] raid; 1st L[ieutenan]t Wayne is dead; with so much misery in the world, he is thankful to God for his mercies to them; mention of becoming a milliner after the war; love to the family.
  - William Mahone, Richmond, Virginia, to Bradley T. Johnson, [Richmond, Virginia], 28 September 1874., 1 page. Cy of ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Desires to know if the enclosed hand bill was "written and authorized to be put out" with his knowledge; if so, whether he approves of it now.
  - Bradley T. Johnson, Richmond, Virginia, to W[illia]m Mahone,[Richmond, Virginia], 28 September 1874., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    The handbill enclosed in [Mahone's] note was written with [Johnson's] knowledge and is now being circulated with his approbation.
  - W[illia]m Mahone, Richmond, Virginia, to Bradley T. Johnson, [Richmond, Virginia], 28 September 1874., 1 page. Cy of ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Has received [Johnson's] reply to his note; in the reply [Johnson] adopts derogatory statements made against Mahone in a handbill; [Mahone] denounces the handbill as a "malicious falsehood" and denounces Mahone as its author.
  - Bradley T. Johnson, Richmond, Virginia, to W[illia]m Mahone,[Richmond, Virginia], 28 September 1874., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Received his last note, handed to him by J[ohn] S[ergeant] Wise; he has telegraphed a friend, and will send a communication when he arrives.
  - Bradley T. Johnson, Richmond, [Virginia], to William Mahone [Richmond, Virginia], 29[?] September [18]74., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    His friend Col. R. Snowden Andrews is fully authorized to act for him and will communicate with any friend he designates.
  - Memorandum by James Barron Hope, describing a conversation with Colonel R. Snowden Andrews concerning the Andrews-Mahone dispute, 29 September 187[4]., 2 pages. AMsS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Discussion of time and place for the duel.
  - Memorandum by R. Snowden Andrews describing a conversation with James Barron Hope, who informed him of Gen. Mahone's arrest, 2 October 1874., 1 page. AMsS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    [James Barron Hope] offered himself in Gen. Mahone's place, which was politely declined.
  - S. Bassett French, Richmond, [Virginia], to James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 21 April 1877., 9 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Upset with views held by those from Rockbridge, Virginia, who opposed railroad consolidation; leaders of this faction included a M. Ganett, a Mr. White, and a Mr. Allan, the latter two of which were professors at Washington College; mentions a state judge, Mr. Anderson, and his son, William, both of whom switched to the anti-consolidation faction; implies that the anti-consolidators bribed state officials; lists the votes of both state houses on the bill chartering the Atlantic, Maryland, and Ohio Road; this letter is just to refresh his memory.
  - Hugh Blair Grigsby, "Edgehill," [Charlotte County, Virginia], to [James Barron] Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 11 October 1879., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Positive response to his [James Barron Hope] letter concerning the Battle of Yorktown centennial celebration; presents legal view of holding Congress to its 1781 pledge of the erection of a statue at Yorktown; lists relatives of Edmund Randolph, who read the pledge in 1781; thinks one of these relatives should read the resolution at the celebration; mentioned the matter to, and received a positive response from, the Massachusetts Historical Society President Robert C. Winthrop; enclosed is a copy of Congress' 1781 resolution; regards to his family.
    Includes Cy of M of Congress [Washington, D. C.]; concerns erection of a marble column at York, Virginia 1 page.
    Includes postscript from [Hugh Blair Grigsby, Edgehill, Charlotte County, Virginia], to [James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia]. The centennial celebration should be a national undertaking; lists what the steps of the celebration should be.
  - [?], n.p., to Capt[ai]n [James Barron] Hope, n.p., [188?]., 2 pages. AL. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Great reception of Hope's speeches, and the honor it has brought, both to him and to the state of Virginia; although these demonstrations are sincere, they are from the "worse half of humanity," to the better half, which speaks "in the vernacular of the heart," must express its thanks in another way; flowers accompanied the letter to show their appreciation; puts Hope on the same literary level as [Edgar Alan] Poe and [John Reuben] Thompson.
  - Edward V. Valentine, Richmond, Virginia, to [James Barron] Hope, n.p., 5 May 1880., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Story once told to him concerning the sculptor [Johann Christian] Rauch; gratification from Hope's understanding of both Homer's literature and his own sculptures; he plans to show "cultivated people" Hope's impressions of his work; his brother is ill; his family sends their regards; looking forward to his next visit.
  - Benj[amin] S. Ewell,[Williamsburg, Virginia], to James Baron Hope, n.p., 28 June 1881. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Encloses a resolution of the College of William and Mary Board of Visitors, concerning "the matter in Oct. 1879" and was "offered by Gen[eral William B.] Taliaferro;" Taliaferro spoke [to Ewell] in kind and grateful terms of [James Barron Hope]; his grandfather Benjamin Stoddert, served in John Adams' cabinet, and he ha inherited his politics; admiration of [James Barron Hope's] consistent course." 1 page. ALS. Bears postscript from B[enjamin] S. Ewell, [Williamsburg, Virginia], to [James Barron Hope], n.p. "the College and Williamsburg will be a part of Norfolk, so do all you can to restore it."
  - Geo[rge] Fred[eric]k Holmes,[Charlottesville, Virginia], to Ja[me]s Barron Hope, Norfolk, [Virginia], 5 December 1881., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Pleasure upon learning that [James Barron Hope] will deliver his "York Town Centennial here;" insists that he stay at his house; it will delight the children, his wife, and himself to reminisce with him.
  - A[braham] C. Myers, Washington, [D. C.], to J[ames] Barron Hope, n.p., 20 January 1882., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Has just learned of his impending visit to Washington, at the invitation of leading Congressmen, to read his Yorktown Centennial Poem; his bad health may prevent his attendance, but he desires to see him; their mutual friend Judge [John Blair] Hope is now a Congressman, and will be equally happy to see him.
  - W. Gordon McCabe, Petersburg, Virginia, to Ja[me]s Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 16 June 1883., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Busy with final examinations, but wants to assure him he would never believe that [James Barron Hope] would "accept any questionable position;" his reliance on [James Barron Hope] and Dick Pegram in the present, "shameless time;" sympathy for his 'tempest of wrath' [?]; love to the wife and family.
  - J[ames] B[arron] H[ope],[Norfolk, Virginia], to John [?], n.p., 17 December 1883., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    He sent 50 copies of Janey's [Janey Barron Hope] story today, which were 20 cents per copy; don't feel obligated to get rid of them all; thinks he will be pleased with the story; Janey seems bent on a career in literature; thanks for "the trouble you took in my own matter;" love to his family.
  - [W.] G[ordon] M[cCabe], Petersburg, Virginia, to James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 19 May 1884., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Arrived safely at home; how much he enjoyed visiting; has read the work sent to him and will send it back soon; describes the work as interesting 'in spots;' insists that [James Barron Hope] and the family visit soon.
  - John Goode, Washington, [D. C.], to [James Barron] Hope, n.p., 12 December 1884., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    The Washington monument is to be dedicated in two months; [Robert] Winthrop is scheduled to speak, and [Oliver Wendell] Holmes is being discussed as the poet of the occasion; he wishes to have [James Barron Hope] selected, since Virginia was "the mother of Washington;" if it is acceptable he will submit his name to the committee; asks for copies of his poems read at Yorktown, Jamestown, and Richmond, if available.
  - Rob[ert] C. Winthrop, Boston, Massachusetts, to J[ames] Barron Hope, n.p., 18 February 1885., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Thanks him for the complimentary editorial in The Landmark; great disappointment at his own illness and consequent inability to speak at the dedication of the Washington Monument; wish that [James Barron Hope] had been assigned an ode for the occasion; his son is sending him a confidential copy of the speech prior to its delivery in Washington; hopes that it is satisfactory; he dare not write any more due to his health; regards.
  - W[illia]m F. Vilas, Washington, D. C., to James Baron Hope, [Norfolk, Virginia], 15 July 1886., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Acknowledgment of both his kind note and gratifying editorial concerning his administration of the Office of the Postmaster General; owes him a debt for his help in guiding public opinion; most deeply pleased by the thought that he [James Barron Hope] has feelings of friendship towards him.
  - W[illia]m F. Vilas, Washington, D. C., to Ja[me]s Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 22 July 1886., 1 page. PLs. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Request for an evaluation of the local postal situation at Newport News, Virginia, and the applicants for the vacant postmaster position in that city.
  - R. C. Taylor, Norfolk, Virginia, to [Jane Barron] Hope [Marr],[Lexington, Virginia?], 20 September 1887., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Enclosed is a copy of the Norfolk City School Board's resolutions concerning the death of James Barron Hope; he [R. C. Taylor, Clerk of the School Board] also begs to convey his deep feelings of admiration and affection for him [James Barron Hope], and his sympathy for the family.
    Includes list containing resolutions following [James Barron Hope's] death, which honor him and also mourn his passing. 1 page. Cy of D.
  - H. T. Jones, Williamsburg, Virginia, to Janie [Barron] Hope Marr, n.p., 10 November 1895., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Recently received her "circular letter" concerning the collection and publication of her father's poems; he found an original poem by [James Barron Hope] in his deceased wife's belongings, and has enclosed a copy of it for her use.
    Includes Cy of poem by [James Barron Hope], "Inscribed to Miss Mollie by her distinguished friend and fellow citizen Jeemes B. Hope." 3 pages.
  - Frederick T. Amiss, Richmond, Virginia, to R[obert] A. Marr, Lexington, Virginia, 13 March 1900., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Enclosed are pamphlet, newspaper clippings, and sample page of "our new pamphlet advertising 'A Wreath of Virginia Bay Leaves';" the four-page pamphlet will be ready soon; his company will do everything in its power to push the sale of this book; anything connected with the V[irginia] M[ilitary] I[nstitute] will receive his special attention; kind regards.
    Includes NswCl from Richmond Times Dispatch concerning A Wreath of Virginia Bay Leaves, n.d. 1 page.
    Includes NwsCl from Norfolk Journal, n.d., praising A Wreath of Virginia Bay Leaves, n.d. 1 page.
    Includes sample of A Wreath of Virginia Bay Leaves. 4 pages. PM
    Includes Tcy of Ms from four-page pamphlet on A Wreath of Virginia Bay Leaves. 1 page. Tcy of Ms.
  - John Critcher, Washington, D. C., to [Janey Barron Hope], n.p., 14 March 1900., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    John W. Goode recently sent him a copy of the Conservative Review of March, 1900, which contained articles by both Goode and her [Janey Barron Hope]; a short time later he read a review of her article in the Norfolk Landmark, which expressed his opinion in much better terms than he himself could write; he [Janey's Uncle] and her aunt are both in good health; love to her mother, her husband and the children.
  - R. S. Thomas, Smithfield, Virginia, to Janey [Barron] Hope Marr,2 May [19]03., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Her father was largely instrumental in "promoting and procuring the monument" at Yorktown; his address read at Yorktown was a great work of prose; would very much like to read it again; also asks if she know where the address of another Yorktown orator, [William G.?] Blaine, might be obtained.
  - J[ohn] L[esslie] Hall, Williamsburg, Virginia, to [Janey Barron Hope Marr], n.p., 22 February 19[07]., 1 page. TLS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    The College of William and Mary desires to display pictures of distinguished alumni at the Jamestown Exposition; requests a photograph or engraving of Hope; following the exhibition the pictures shall be hung in the library.
  - J[ohn] Lesslie Hall, Williamsburg, Virginia, to [Janey Barron Hope Marr], [Blacksburg, Virginia], 26 February 1907., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Pleased to hear that she can furnish a picture of her father; needs a medium-sized picture to go with a group of William and Mary literati; other items sent will adorn the walls of the Carnegie Library; asks if James or Samuel Barron were William and Mary students; whether they were or not, their pictures can be used by the college; William and Mary has two copies of Virginia Bay Leaves, and will display one at the exhibition; he has quoted from it in his new book Half Hours in Southern Literature; Pres[ident Lyon G.] Tyler has her father's picture in his new edition of The Cradle of the Republic, just released.
  - L[uther] C[ampbell] Lindsley, Williamsburg, Virginia, to Janey [Barron] Hope Marr, Blacksburg, Virginia, 15 December 1907., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    The College Magazine will publish a poem by one of its distinguished literary alumni during each month from January to June; will begin with its greatest poet, James Barron Hope; would like to publish "A Little Picture", and also borrow the engraving of his portrait.
  - Cary F. Jacob, Williamsburg, Virginia, to [Janey Barron Hope] Marr, Norfolk, Virginia, 1 February 1920., 1 page. TLS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    He has been asked by the State Board of Education to prepare a series of pictures telling the history of Virginia literature; requests a list of places associated with her father; would also like to have a list of contemporary Virginians that should be included in his list; regrets that he cannot include the work of Mrs. [J.] Westmore Wil[l]cox, due to its subject matter.
  - [Janey Barron Hope Marr], Norfolk, Virginia, to [Cary F.] Jacob,[Williamsburg, Virginia], 3 February 1920., 2 pages. Cy of TL. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Pleased to learn that he is giving his talents to "dear 'Old William and Mary';" gratifying that Virginia has not forgotten James Barron Hope; suggestions of places relating to her father, including the statue at Jamestown and the Lee statue in Richmond; brief biography of Hope; mention of her father's address to the Phi Beta Kappa Society and graduating classes of William and Mary on July 4, 1858; list of contemporary Virginia writers worthy of his investigation.
  Series 2: Writings
- Writtings, n.d. (Box 1-2)
  - Poetry, n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Poem [by James Barron Hope]; opening line: "Seeking the Poem in its perfect bloom", n.d., 22 pages. Poem. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Poem, The Teacher of his Age,[by James Barron Hope], n.d., 1 page. Df of Poem. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Poem, Moonrise on the Chesapeake,[by James Barron Hope], n.d., 1 page. Df of Poem. (Box-folder 1:8)
      Bears NwsCl of poem, Sunset; taken from the Norfolk Landmark.
    - Poem, Evening on Hampton Roads,[by James Barron Hope]; written for the Norfolk Landmark, n.d., 1 page. Df of poem. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Poem, Swift, [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 1 page. Df of Poem. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Incomplete poem, second page beginning "The fidders they all fiddled"; [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 12 pages. Page 1 is missing. Poem. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Incomplete poem [by James Barron Hope], beginning "Plain men have fitful moods...", n.d., 1 page. Fragment. (Box-folder 1:8)
      Includes sketch of ballerina on reverse side. 1 page. ASk.
    - Last page of poem [by James Barron Hope]; first line: "Ah realm of tombs! but (let us) bear"; on subject of Virginia and [Robert E.] Lee,n.d., 1 page. Fragment. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Part of page 19 of a poem [by James Barron Hope]; first line: "Tho' all within, good spirits, hold dominion," n.d., 1 page. Fragment. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Incomplete doggerel verse, beginning "I am told that a good moral," [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 1 page. AMs. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Prose Stories, Remarks, and Notes, 1856-1874, n.d. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Incomplete prose story, "The Baron of Leibenstien," [by James Barron Hope], [1856]., 1 page. AMs. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Poem, The Rector of Sherwood, [by James Barron Hope], [1857]., 4 pages. Poem. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Remarks [by James Barron Hope] concerning the circumstances surrounding the near duel between Bradley T. Johnson and William Mahone in 1874; Hope was Mahone's second, [post 3 October 1874 - ante December 1874?]., 6 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Notes on grammar for Norfolk school; includes the Lord's Prayer, the Lord's Prayer in Saxon, and notes on spelling, 1886., 13 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Written in the hand of James Barron Hope.
    - Short composition, The Vase of Diana,[by James Barron Hope], n.d., 2 pages. AMsS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Incomplete poem [by James Barron Hope]; first page (page 6) begins "From yonder stream, where the bridge is arched", n.d., 7 pages. Pages 6-12. Poem. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Incomplete poem [by James Barron Hope]; opening line: "Seeking the Poem in its ancient tomb", n.d., 9 pages. Pages 1-5, 9-10, 19-20. Cy of poem. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Draft of a poem [by James Barron Hope]; opening line: "Sleep'st thou my muse, why com'st thou not to cheer?", n.d., 3 pages. Df of poem. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Second and third pages are almost exact copies of first.
    - Poem [by James Barron Hope]; opening line: "One hundred years ago"; [probably delivered orally in Lynchburg, Virginia], n.d., 5 pages. Poem. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Book Manuscripts, n.d. (Box 1-2)
    - Untitled prose story [by James Barron Hope]; first line: "How long Ms. O'Rocekity and", n.d., 15 pages. Drama. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Prose story, Our Boys In Grey,[by James Barron Hope], n.d., 8 pages. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Prose story, John Bull and the Bear,[by James Barron Hope], n.d., 3 pages. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Incomplete manuscript of Under the Empire; Or The Story Of Madelon,n.d., 21 leaves. Includes [but not limited to] Chapters XXII - XXIV. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Incomplete prose story [by James Barron Hope], set in France; first line: "Imagine an improvement on", n.d., 10 leaves. [Chapter 6?]. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 1:13)